Guide to the Leo Stein Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Leo Stein Collection
1892-1950
YCAL MSS 78
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
19.25
(22 boxes) + 56 broadside folders
The Leo Stein Collection contains manuscripts of writings by Stein, letters from such persons as: Bernard Berenson, Mabel Dodge Luhan and Maurice Sterne, personal papers, photographs, and artworks (mainly by Stein), which document the life of Leo Stein, an artist and writer. Many letters to Leo Stein for the period before 1913 can be found in the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers, YCAL MSS 76, also owned by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Stein, Leo, 1872-1947
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Leo Stein Collection was acquired over several years, principally as a bequest of the estate of Leo and Nina Stein, given in 1960 through Joseph Solomon, literary executor for Leo Stein. However, many items had been given to the Yale Collection of American Literature by various parties in the years preceding. Subsequent gifts, particularly from Stein family members, completed this assemblage.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Correspondence received by Leo Stein before 1913 can be found in the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers, YCAL MSS 76.
LEO STEIN (1872-1947)
Leo Stein was born in Allegheny, Pennsylvania, in 1872, the fourth surviving child in the family of Daniel and Amelia Stein. In 1874, his sister, Gertrude, was born. Due to the changing fortunes of the family and the difference in ages between siblings, Leo and Gertrude came, in a sense, to raise each other, their own fates linked for several decades. [A timeline provided in the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers pinpoints significant events in their lives.] In brief, Leo attended Harvard for several years, took a trip around the world with his cousin Fred Stein in 1895, and matriculated to Johns Hopkins along with Gertrude, where he was awarded a bachelor of arts degree in 1898. The two established housekeeping in Paris in 1903 at 27 Rue de Fleurus, by which time Leo had happened upon a vocation. He began to paint and continued until his death producing landscapes and nudes. These early years in Paris were spent acquiring paintings, as well. Gertrude and Leo collected works by the then little-known artists Pablo Picasso, Henri Matisse, and Paul Cezanne.
The first ten years in Paris were busy and fruitful, with Leo pursuing his art and Gertrude her writing. They both fell in love. Leo with Nina Auzias, an artist's model, and Gertrude with Alice B. Toklas, a fellow expatriate from California. These changes in their lives, however, were what helped to precipitate their eventual break. Perhaps due to Leo's jealousy over Alice, perhaps due to Gertrude's frustration at Leo's dismissal of her work, in 1913, when the two were on either side of 40, they parted for good. Leo took Nina to live with him in Settignano, Italy, and Gertrude remained in Paris on the Rue de Fleurus with Alice. Leo wrote occasionally to Gertrude, usually to clarify matters of their estates, but the acrimonious rift would never be healed.
Leo spent several years in North America during World War I, separated from Nina. He continued to paint, and to write critically about art, but his principal interest in these later years was psychoanalysis. He would spend significant amounts of time, money, and energy during the subsequent decades undergoing intense Freudian therapy to undo the burdensome neuroses he described so often in letters to friends. He finally married Nina in 1921, and sold the bulk of his art collection to the American collector Albert Barnes in the 1920s. In 1927, he published a collection of his critical writings on art as The A-B-C of Aesthetics. He continued writing over the next two decades, proposing to collect more of his essays which brought together his ruminations on aesthetics, metaphysics, philosophy, and psychoanalysis. In 1947, he brought out this compilation as Appreciation: Painting, Poetry and Prose. He had just begun to receive laudatory critical reviews of the book when he was informed that his ongoing stomach problems were caused by cancer. He died on July 29, 1947, barely one year later than his sister Gertrude had died, and of the same ailment that had killed her. He was survived only by his wife Nina, who lived on in Settignano for two years until committing suicide in 1949.
Leo's cousin Fred Stein, along with several friends, gathered together a selection of Leo Stein's letters and writings as a tribute to him. They were published in 1950 as Journey Into the Self.
Scope and Contents
The Leo Stein Collection contains manuscripts, letters, and artworks by Leo Stein, which document his life and work, principally in the latter part of his life. The collection spans the years 1892-1950.
The collection is housed in 22 boxes and 56 broadside folders, and is organized into six series: Correspondence, Notebooks, Writings, Personal Papers, Photographs, and Artworks. Box 22 contains Oversize material.
Series I, Correspondence, is divided into three subseries: Outgoing, Incoming, and Third-Party. The Outgoing series contains mainly original letters donated by recipients, though a number of carbons retained by Leo Stein are found here as well. Among the persons included in both the Outgoing and the Incoming subseries are Leo's wife, Nina Auzias Stein, family members such as Fred Stein and Howard and Bird Sternberger Gans, Leo's college friend, Mabel Foote Weeks, Otakar Coubine [Kubin], a fellow painter he encouraged, George Boas, Bernard Berenson, Hiram Haydn, and Miriam and Joe Price. Among the other items of correspondence in the Incoming section are letters Leo Stein received concerning aesthetics and psychoanalysis from fellow writers: Adolphe Basler, Trigant Burrow, John Dewey, Manuel Komroff, R. C. Trevelyan, and about art in general from artists and collectors: Albert Barnes, Edward Bruce, Leon Kroll. Included here are letters from many of his friends, such as Norman Douglas, Mabel Dodge Luhan, Daniel and Roselle Mebane, James and Conevah Osgood, Morgan Russell, and Adele Wolman. This subseries includes letters received by Nina Stein and by Chantal Quenneville, hence the dates extending through 1949.
The Third Party correspondence pertains mainly to the settling of Leo Stein's estate and the publication of Journey Into the Self, as seen in letters between Fred Stein, Hiram Haydn, Nina Stein, and Chantal Quenneville (a long-time friend of Nina Stein's). A typescript of Fred Stein's memoir of traveling around the world with Leo Stein in 1896 is included with the letters from Fred Stein to Hiram Haydn.
Series II, Notebooks and Journals, begins with a group of holograph notebooks which served all purposes for Stein: notepad, sketchbook, commonplace book, and letter-pad. They are organized according to a numbering system apparently ascribed when they were used in the preparation of Journey Into the Self. The material in these notebooks is free-form. Though many jottings take the shape of essays, there is no distinct relation between these sketchy notes and the drafts of writings in Series III. The three journals which follow are more clearly identifiable as records of daily events during the Second World War. (The existence or whereabouts of other journals is not known.)
Series III, Writings, is composed principally of the writings of Leo Stein although Writings of Others are also present. Stein's writings include titled manuscripts, including ones for which titles could be assigned, as well as numerous folders of untitled manuscripts and fragments. Among the titled manuscripts are draft materials for Appreciation: Poetry, Painting and Prose and Journey into the Self (gathered posthumously). The only distinct evidence of The A B C of Aesthetics is a selection of reviews, though parts which made up this collection may well be found here under other titles. Many other articles for such publications as The New Republic are present in typescript or printed versions. The untitled manuscripts and fragments are filed at the end of the series in no particular order, as none could be determined. The majority of these untitled pieces deal with the recurrent themes of aesthetics, art and psychoanalysis. Among the Writings of Others are several printed pieces on art and a collection of various manuscripts by Nina Stein.
Series IV, Personal Papers, includes a group of clippings about Gertrude Stein, annotated by Leo, Leo's diploma from Johns Hopkins, and receipts for artwork by Otakar Coubine.
Series V, Photographs, principally contains prints of Leo and Nina Stein and several of their friends. Included here are a series of snapshots apparently taken during a visit to Mabel Dodge Luhan's home in Taos, as well as a number of prints of artworks, mainly by Edward Bruce.
Series VI, Artwork by Leo Stein, gathers together the principal body of his output. Drawn from the Stein estate and from several gifts, this series is divided into groups by format and subject. The majority is arranged in the order in which they were inventoried during a campus-wide fine art survey conducted in the early 1980s by Yale Art Gallery staff, as evidenced by inventory numbers affixed to the canvases or boards. (The two exceptions to this being the paintings received from Cone and Keck, which were not inventoried and are arranged in the order they were received.) Central subjects tend to be landscapes (most likely of the Italian hills around Settignano) and studies of female nudes. The oil paintings on canvas had been removed from their stretchers by the time the collection was processed in 1995.
The single item in the Oversize section is a photograph from Series V.
Americans -- France -- History -- 20th Century; Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Modernism (Art); Paris (France) -- Intellectual life; Photographic prints; Artists; Authors; Barnes, Albert C. (Albert Coombs), 1872-1951; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Boas, George, 1891-1980; Burrow, Trigant, 1875-1950; Douglas, Norman, 1868-1952; Haydn, Hiram Collins, 1907-1973; Komroff, Manuel, 1890-1974; Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1879-1962; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Stein, Leo, 1872-1947; Sterne, Maurice, 1878-1957
- Correspondence, 1892-1950; Series I; 2.25; (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries. Incoming and Outgoing are arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Third-Party, arranged alphabetically by author.
  - OUTGOING
    - Berenson, Bernard, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boas, George H., 1924-28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Coubine, Otakar, 1926-47 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      Includes: typescript carbon of "Coubine" (1927)
    - Gallinaro [?], Dr., ca. 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gans, Bird Sternberger, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Gans, Howard, 1945-46, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Haydn, Hiram, 1947 Jul 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Kallen, [Horace?], [ca. 1927] (Box 1, Folder 10)
      [draft]
    - [Komroff?], Manuel, 1946 Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Kubin, Otakar
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Coubine, Box 1, folder 3
    - Pach, [Walter], 1929 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Price, Miriam and Joe, 1925, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Quenneville, Chantal, 1935, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Russell, Bertrand (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Stein, Fred, 1892-1947 (Box 1, Folder 16-25)
      Includes: postscripts by GS (1892)
    - Stein, Nina Auzias, 1909-1914 (Box 1, Folder 26-30)
    - Stein, Nina Auzias, 1915-1946, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31-45)
    - Stein, Michael, 1892-1914, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Stein, Sarah [and Michael], 1895-96 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Stein, S., Mr. and Mrs., 1895-96 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Sterne, Maurice, [ca. 1938-39] (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Time Magazine, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Weeks, Mabel Foote, 1900-1947, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51-59)
    - Uncle Sol, 1895 Aug 17 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 61)
      [fragment]
  - INCOMING
    - "A" general, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Adler, Mortimer J., [1927?] (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Asch, Nathan, 1924 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Auzias, Paul, 1947 Jul (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - "B" general, 1933-47 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Barnes, Albert, 1924-25 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Basler, Adolphe, 1926-34, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Berenson, Bernard Berenson, Mary, 1928-47, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Boas, George, 1927[?]-47, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Boni and Liveright, 1927, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Bruce, Edward Bruce, Peggy, 1926-49, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 72)
      Includes: letters to Leo and Nina
    - Bruin, Maloney-Louise, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Burrow, Trigant, 1925-47 (Box 3, Folder 74)
      Includes: typescript of "Psychoanalysis Psychoanalyzed"
    - Coubine, Otakar Coubine, Bertha, 1926-49, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 75-77)
    - "D" general, 1921-47, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Dewey, John, 1925-26 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      Includes: drafts of letter from LS
    - Douglas, Norman, 1922-46, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - "F" general, 1945-47 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - [Forman, J---?], 1934-35, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Frank, Waldo, 1928, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Gans, Howard Gans, Bird Sternberger, 1932-46 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Ghyka, C. Y., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Hackett, Francis, 1917 Oct 26 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Hallowell, Robert, 1926, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Hapgood, Hutchins, 1941 Jan 11 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Harris, Marjorie, 1930 May 11 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Hartley, Marsden, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Haydn, Hiram, 1946-49 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - "J-K" general, 1931, 1933, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Jones, Howard Mumford, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Kallen, Horace, 1928 Jun 27 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Keyser, Ebb, 1921, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Komroff, Manuel, 1927-35 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Kroll, Leon, 1926, 1936, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Kubin, Otakar
      See: Coubine
    - "L" general, 1932, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Lawrence, D. H., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, [1911-35?] (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - "M" general, 1924, 1947, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Mebane, Daniel Mebane, Roselle, 1930-45, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Montale, Eugenio, 1935 Mar (Box 4, Folder 103)
      Includes: letter from EM to The New Yorker and from The New Yorker to LS
    - Neumann, J. B., 1929-33 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Nichols, Herbert, 1928 Dec (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Norman, Dorothy, 1946 Sep 2 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Oppenheimer, Ben, 1945, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Osgood, James Osgood, Conevah [?], 1931-47, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Pach, Walter, 1929, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Paget, Violet [Vernon Lee], 1920 Apr 24 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Perry, Ralph Barton, 1928 Jan 24 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Price, Miriam Sutro Price, Joe, 1947-49, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Purrmann, Hans, 1945, 1947, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Raffel, Dan Raffel, Gertrude, 1945-48 (Box 4, Folder 114)
      Includes: transcriptions of diary entries (1884)
    - Rigby, Elizabeth, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Russell, Morgan, 1934-47 (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - Sandburg, Carl, 1926 Jun 7 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Sargent, Porter, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Simonson, Lee, 1933, 1947, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Smith, Logan Pearsall, 1938 Apr 7 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Stein, Fred, 1926-49 (Box 5, Folder 121-122)
      Includes: drafts of letters by LS and letters to and from Nina Stein
    - Stein, Nina Auzias, 1910-47 (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Stein, Rose Ellen, 1945-46 (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Stein, Sarah, 1935, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Sterne, Maurice, 1903-38, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 126-127)
    - [Sterne?], May, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1928, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - "T" general, 1934, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Tennyson, Hallam (1921- ), 1945, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Titterton, W.R., 1905-07, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Trench, Herbert, 1920-21, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 133)
      Includes: Holograph and typescript poems by HT
    - Trevelyan, R.C., 1920-47 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Uhde, Wilhelm, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - "W-Z" general, 1945-46, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Weeks, Mabel Foote, 1930-48, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Whitehouse, Joyce, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Wolman, Adele, 1934-49, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 139)
      Includes: letter from LS (n.d.)
    - Unidentified "Ben", 1933 Sep 15 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Unidentified "Laura", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 141)
  - THIRD PARTY
    - Aldred, Anderson to Mabel Dodge Luhan, 1917 Nov 13 (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Blevins, Robert L. to American Scholar, 1947 Jul 9 (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Boni & Liveright to Richard Guggenheimer, 1935 Mar 26 (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Braxton, Lina to C.G. Paulding, 1947 Sep 30 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Bruce, Margaret to Fred Stein, 1949 May 10 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Fuller, Edmund to Hiram Haydn, 1949 Jul 5 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Greenleigh, Arthur to American Joint Distribution Committee, New York, 1944 Dec 10 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Guggenheimer, Richard to Fred Stein, 1948 Jul (Box 5, Folder 149)
      Includes: typescript carbon of response from FS
    - Haydn, Hiram to Chantal Quenneville, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Preble, Gertrude [sec'y to Fred Stein] to Chantal Quenneville, 1950 Dec 13 (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - Quenneville, Chantal to Fred Stein, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 152)
      Includes: typescript carbons of replies from FS and letter from FS to Edmund Fuller
    - S., Gustina to Nina Stein, 1949, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - Spiegelberg, George to Fred Stein, 1948 Oct (Box 5, Folder 154)
    - Stein, Fred to George Boar, 1947 Apr 7 (Box 5, Folder 155)
    - Stein, Fred to Hiram Haydn, 1948-49 (Box 5, Folder 156)
      Includes: typescript of memoir of Leo Stein by FS
    - Stein, Fred to Henry C. Kleeman, 1947 Jun 3 (Box 5, Folder 157)
    - Stein, Fred to Oliviero Olivieri, 1947 Jan (Box 5, Folder 158)
    - Stein, Fred to Walter Pach, 1947 May 28 (Box 5, Folder 159)
    - Stein, Fred to Chantal Quenneville, 1948-50 (Box 5, Folder 160)
    - Stein, Nina to Paul [Auzias?], 1947 Nov 24 (Box 5, Folder 161)
    - Stein, Nina to Hiram Haydn, 1948 Jun 7 (Box 5, Folder 162)
    - Stein, Nina to Maria [draft], 1948 Feb 16 (Box 5, Folder 163)
    - [Stein, Nina?] to Mr. Parsons [draft], 1947 Sep (Box 5, Folder 164)
    - Stein, Nina to Chantal Quenneville, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 165)
      [photocopies]
    - Stein, Nina to Fred Stein, 1947-49 (Box 5, Folder 166)
      Includes: typescript carbon of responses by FS
    - Stein, Maurice to Fred Stein, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 167)
    - Strasser, Arthur to Fred Stein, 1946 Sep (Box 5, Folder 168)
- Notebooks and Journals, 1920-1944; Series II; 1.5; (4 boxes)
  Series II, Notebooks and Journals, is organized into two subseries. Notebooks are arranged numerically, followed by unnumbered items which are arranged alphabetically. Journals are arranged chronologically.
  - NOTEBOOKS
    - [#1]: "Aphorisms" [on art, morality and psychology] (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - [#2]: [notes for chapters on Matisse and Picasso] (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - [#3]: [notes re: emotion, instinct, and aesthetics; sketches] (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - [#4]: "Poems" and "APHS" [aphorisms, notes on literature; draft of letter to "Ben"] (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - [#5]: [notes re: painters, philosophers, and aesthetics] (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - [#6]: [notes re: belief, instinct, knowledge; draft of letter to Mabel Weeks?], n.d. (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - [#7]: [notes re: time and space, sexual neuroses, art; sketches] (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - [#9]: "Book" [notes re: aesthetics; draft of letter to Mr. Rosenfarb; sketches, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - [#10]: "Quotations and Notes Vol II" [also includes poems, clippings, and aphorisms] (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - [#11]: "Wm. James" [notes], n.d. (Box 7, Folder 178)
    - "James II" [notes re: William James; list of book titles], n.d. (Box 7, Folder 179)
    - [#12]: "Fragments" [notes re: art and philosophy; sketches] (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - [#13]: "T III" [chapters re: self-consciousness and art] (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - [#14]: [aphorisms and quotations; photostat of letter from Allen S. Weller to Howard Gans, 1945 Apr 20] (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - [#15]: "Text Vol. I" [notes re: psychology and sexual neuroses, sketches, anecdotes; draft of cable to Nina Stein] (Box 7, Folder 183)
    - [#16]: "Sketch of an Aesthetics" [chapters for a book], n.d. (Box 7, Folder 184)
    - [#17]: "Quotations, Prose, and Poetry" [aphorisms, draft of letter, clippings, sketches], ca. 1940-41 (Box 7, Folder 185)
    - "1 P.A." [journal entries re: psychoanalysis and sexual neuroses], 1920 Jan (Box 8, Folder 186)
    - "1929" [notes re: the self, the real, knowledge] (Box 8, Folder 187)
    - "4" [journal entries re: psychoanalysis and sexual neuroses], [1920?] (Box 8, Folder 188)
    - "Esthetics" [notes re: aesthetics; journal entries re: psychoanalysis], 1920 Jan-Feb (Box 8, Folder 189)
    - "Text, the Real" [notes re: knowledge, the real, aesthetics], n.d. (Box 8, Folder 190)
    - [missing cover--beginning "Incipit Vita Nuova" - journal entries re: psychoanalysis and philosophy], 1929 (Box 8, Folder 191)
    - [notes re: art, philosophy, science and efficiency] (Box 8, Folder 192)
    - [notes re: magic, the self, the real; sketches], n.d. (Box 8, Folder 193)
    - [fragment re: Mary Calkins, identification, intelligence], n.d. (Box 9, Folder 194)
    - [fragment re: philosophy], n.d. (Box 9, Folder 195)
  - JOURNALS
    - [Journal; includes entries in another hand], 1941 (Box 9, Folder 196)
    - [Journal], 1942-44 (Box 9, Folder 197)
    - "During the War", 1944 (Box 9, Folder 198)
- Writings, 1910-1950; Series III; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Series III, Writings, is organized into two subseries. Writings of Leo Stein are arranged alphabetically by title. Writings of Others is arranged alphabetically by name.
  - WRITINGS OF LEO STEIN
    - The A B C of Aesthetics, reviews, 1927-28 (Box 10, Folder 199-200)
      Includes printed versions of Leo Stein letters to The New Republic and review by Hans C. Syz, typescript carbon, corrected, and review by unidentified [in German], typescript carbon, corrected
    - [Account of his early friendship and travel with Fred M. Stein], typescript (Box 10, Folder 201)
    - Albert Ryder, printed version, corrected, [ The New Republic ?], [1918 Apr 7?] (Box 10, Folder 202)
    - Appreciation: Poetry, Painting and Prose
      - Typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 203-204)
      - Foreword, typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 205)
      - [fragments], typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 206)
      - Reviews, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 207)
        [includes printed version of Leo Stein letter to Time ]
    - The Arch in New York City, printed version, corrected, The New Republic, 1919 Jan 11 (Box 10, Folder 208)
    - [Art], typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 209)
    - Art and Mysticism, typescript corrected (Box 10, Folder 210)
    - Art and Society, printed version, The New Republic, 1914 Apr 26 (Box 10, Folder 211)
    - Art and the Frame, printed version, annotated, The New Republic, 1926 Mar 24 (Box 10, Folder 212)
    - The Defeat of John Ruskin, printed version, corrected, The New Republic, 1919 Feb 8 (Box 10, Folder 213)
    - The Defense of the Self, typescript, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 214)
    - Degas and the Draughtsmanship, printed version, corrected, The New Republic, 1917 Nov 3 (Box 10, Folder 215)